Hope you had a wonderful long weekend.
So, let's jump right into it. So, where did we leave last time? Last time we talked about the power of the situation.
We talked about how beliefs become self-fulfilling prophecies and how it is through the situation that we very often create expectations,
beliefs of people, and these beliefs become reality.
And we talked about how social psychology essentially started with some very important experiments such as the Milgram effect or obedience to authority, such as Zimbardo's prison experiment where prisoners were put in or students played the role of prisoners or the role of wardens.
and they actually entered that role so totally that after a week the experiment had to be stopped when it was supposed to go on for two weeks.
And then the question we asked was, okay, so we know that the situation is powerful. We know that it makes a difference.
Can we also create a powerful, positive situation to bring out the best in people?
And the answer is yes. And we started talking about it and we talked about Professor Langer and her research.
and how she showed that putting elderly men in an environment where they acted as if they were 20 years younger
actually became younger to the point of having higher levels of intelligence, to the point of improving their memory, improving their eyesight, improving their hearing.
The distance between the bones in their fingers actually became longer, which is a sign of younger age.
They were rated by others as well as by themselves as stronger and younger just because they acted as if it was 1959 instead of what it really was,
which was 1979, the power of the positive situation.
And then she did more research on people going for an eyesight test and then putting them in a situation in a flight simulator.
And the exact same eyesight test, they actually performed better just because of the situation.
And we moved on, and that's where we ended last time, by talking about priming.
Priming can be done on the conscious or subconscious level.
It means planting a seed, planting a belief, planting a word or a picture in our mind,
consciously or subconsciously, and how that actually influences our behavior.
So Barj, that time of NYU, did the research where he primed people with words associated with old.
Words, if you remember, such as wrinkles, words such as old, words such as Florida.
And as a result of this priming, those participants in the study actually walked slower,
were actually more stooped when evaluated by researchers who were not aware of their condition, meaning they didn't know whether they were primed with control words, just random words,
or with words associated with old. So it was just through the priming that people actually started to behave differently.
The power of the situation, the power of the environment.
And then Barj took it a step further and said, okay, let's prime them with positive primes, such as achievement, such as persistence, such as success.
These words, for example, they had to find a synonym for the word achievement.
Those who were primed with these words on intelligence tests and on memory tests actually performed better than the control group who wasn't primed with these words.
to Dutch researchers, Dekerstes and Knippenberg.
What they found was that they brought people in and they asked them to describe for a future experiment, not for that experiment, for a future experiment, asked them to describe the typical day or typical characteristics
of three archetypes, a soccer hooligan, a secretary, and a professor.
described these three archetypes. And they told them that this is for the next experiment where we just want people to evaluate these archetypes,
not knowing that actually by describing these archetypes, these individuals were primed.
They were primed for a soccer hooligan, for a secretary, or for a professor. And then they had to do intelligence tests afterwards,
memory tests after those primes. Those who had to describe the day of a soccer hooligan performed the worst in terms of memory, in terms of intelligence.
Then there was the secretary, and those who performed the best were those who described the professor.
Now, they didn't study any harder before.
Nothing changed except for the fact that there was a prime. There was something planted from the environment in their minds.
The question then is, how can we create a positive environment for ourselves
where we are primed by the positive, where we can be happier, more successful, and so on.
And there are many ways in which we can do it. Let me share a few. In fact, this is going to be your assignment for this week, or one of the assignments, to create a positive environment. So here are some of the examples.
have pictures of people you love or places you love. The important thing about these things is that even if you don't see them, you see them.
So on the subconscious level, it's still there.
Even though on the subconscious level, when people are primed, they don't really see the word, say, achievement on the screen when it's there for 25 milliseconds.
They don't really see it, but it registers.
So even if a picture is there and you don't quote-unquote really see it or are not really conscious of it, mindful of it, it still has an impact on you.
So have pictures of people you love. Have pleasant objects, whether it's memorabilia, whether it's flowers, whether it's art, your favorite art.
So I have in my house and my office my favorite art on the wall by my favorite artists. And let me share with you a few. I actually brought them here.
These are very valuable. I insured them, so it's not a problem.
So this is this specific artist from the first phase of his career.
As you can see, very powerful strokes, very intense, very deliberate, and just gorgeous.
And here is by the same artist from the second phase of his career.
Here you already begin to see impressionist influence on his work. But still, you know, you see the same trend, the same power, the same intensity.
So I have these on my wall.
There's a new and upcoming artist whom I want to introduce you to.
She still doesn't have a second phase. You know, she's only one year old. But, you know, this is work done with the help of her mom.
But again, these are on my wall, and they remind me every day. And even if I've seen them hundreds of times, it's still there when I think about my kids.
And then I also have other lesser-known artists work on my wall.
Again, this is, probably have not heard of this one.
This is Rodin, the thinker.
And so I have this on my wall. It's my favorite sculpture. And then I have another piece by Rodin, just to remind me that it's not all about thinking.
There are other things that make life worth living.
So this is Rodan's The Kiss, for those of you who know it.
And again, have these things on your wall. Create an environment where you feel warm, where it's fun for you to be there.
Quotes.
You know I love quotes.
And I know that many of you love quotes. Some of you have sent me your favorite quotes.
I have on my wall a list of quotes. And they're there, and even if I don't see them, I see them.
so for example let's see if I brought some here yeah, here they are
so one is by John Quincy Adams patience and perseverance have a magical effect before which difficulties disappear and obstacles vanish so priming the issue of persistence
by the way, which is one thing that Barge did he primed that and people actually became more persistent
George Eliot or also known as Marianne Evans my favorite author As she wrote, the important work of moving the world forward does not wait to be done by perfect men.
I'll talk about perfectionism, which is a very personal theme for me in about three weeks.
So she's very much a role model.
Camus, in the depth of winter, I finally learned that there was within me an invincible summer. A quote that has helped me through difficult, through hard times.
Henry David Thoreau. So, if one advances confidently in the direction of his dreams and endeavors to live the life which he has imagined,
he will meet with the success unexpected in common hours. Again, I have these quotes up on my wall and a few others, many of the quotes that you see in the course.
And they prime me, they remind me, they create the environment for me.
We'll talk about art in the next section, in its importance. Have your favorite books next to you. Listen to music, but listen to it mindfully, not just as background music,
but music that inspires you, whether it's Rocky, whether it's Eminem, whoever it is.
Watch films that inspire you.
All these things help you to create an environment that is conducive to growth, to success, to well-being.
A lot of it is done on the subconscious level, which is the power of the priming studies.
and finally this is what positive research is about if we constantly focus on negative research anxiety, depression, schizophrenia
we're primed by this research we're primed by this work and it creates reality this indirectly and tangentially relates to the Eisenberg principle
is that when you measure a phenomenon you're changing the phenomenon when you measure a phenomenon you're also changing yourself
So by researching the positive, we're also priming ourselves with the positive.
Now, a lot of this work that I'm talking about today and that I'll talk about next time actually comes from the self-help movement.
In many ways, the self-help movement was founded, was started, at least in the 20th century,
was started with the understanding that we create the world through our thinking, that our mind creates the world.
and books like these came out back in the 1930s think and grow rich this book since 1930 sold over 60 million copies
it's still selling it's a best seller in the US it's the best seller in China and India it's the best seller in Africa it's the best seller in Europe
it has an impact on people and here is one of the things that Napoleon Hill says whatever your mind can conceive and believe
it can achieve whatever you mind can conceive and believe it can achieve very empowering and
this had an impact on many different people on the masses again 60 million copies one of the best
sellers in history henry ford had a similar idea whether you think you can or can't you are right
and people were drawn to this message why because it's empowering because it makes them feel that Things are possible.
Another very influential book, The Power of Positive Thinking, Norman Vincent Perra.
Have great hopes and dare to go out for them. Have great dreams and dare to live them.
Have tremendous expectations and believe in them.
How inspiring for people to hear that.
All you need to do is think. All you need to do is believe.
And affluence will come to you. whether it's interpersonal affluence, whether it's monetary affluence.
And this has been a message that has drawn the masses and continues to do so today.
The best-selling book today, number one bestseller all over the world.
That's right, The Secret.
The secret to success is what they call the law of attraction. The law of attraction is that you attract to your life whatever you imagine,
whatever you believe in. Again, a powerful message.
Millions and millions of copies of this book being sold.
As we speak, continue to be sold.
And the message is again simple. Believe and you will achieve.
Conceive
and it will be conceived
in reality, in the world. It will come to you.
Very convincing, very inspiring message. But, is this message right?
Well, we talked about this and we saw the Roger Bannister story.
You know, one day or six weeks after Roger Bannister runs the mile in four minutes,
or 359, John Landy runs it in 357.9. The year after, 37 runners run the mile in under four minutes. So there is something to it.
Once they believed it was possible, it became possible.
And here is the issue. with much of what's going on in the self-help realm today.
It draws on a truth, a real truth, and then blows it out of proportion.
So yes, there is some truth in the fact that our mind creates reality.
But that's only part of the truth.
We create reality, or rather we co-create reality.
There has to be something out there or in there. For example, when it comes to the secret, you believe that you're likely to succeed, you're much more likely to succeed,
but that has to come with a lot of hard work and persistence. It has to come with a lot of failure and learning from that failure.
So it's just half of the equation. And what these self-help books and messages do is over-promise and under-deliver, which at times can be destructive.
For example, if everything is based on the law of attraction, I create everything, then everything is up to me and also everything is my fault.
Even taken to the extreme, is a three-year-old girl responsible for being abused?
Is a 30-year-old man responsible for being paralyzed as a result of an accident by a drunken driver?
there are certain things that are out there and when we say that everything is up to us everything is created by the law of attraction
then it's a prescription
maybe in the short term for inspiration and for belief and for well-being but in the long term it's for frustration, for guilt
and for unhappiness
and also for less success because if I really believe that it's all about thinking then this is going to be my mindset All I need to do is believe, and then all the money will come to me.
All the success in a relationship will come to me, and that does away with the hard work, with the persistence, with the failure
that is necessary, part and parcel of a successful, happy, fulfilling human life.
I want to show you a quick video. This is of an ad I saw online, and I actually called the Royal Bank of Scotland and ask them to send me the original
because it captures some of the misunderstanding that there is today about the power of the mind. Just a very cute ad.
Douglas, from the conference.
James Anderson. Oh, yeah. That's right.
That's a lot of green.
What kind of bird is it?
It's okay, guys.
I've done a course.
What?
Positive thinking.
Positive thought makes a positive impact.
It captures part of the truth, but not the whole truth.
So let's see what serious research has to say about the power of the mind. A real phenomenon, an actual phenomenon, but one that we need to also apply real research to and see what works.
Albert Bendura, whom you're reading about for this week, has done a lot of work on the concept of self-efficacy,
which is essentially the academic term for believing in oneself. And here is what he writes after decades and decades of research.
He, by the way, won the researcher's prize for the positive psychologist last year. So he's doing a lot of research in this area. He's from Stanford.
Beliefs in personal efficacy affect life choices, level of motivation, quality of functioning,
resilience to adversity, and vulnerability to stress and depression.
Those who believe in themselves, who have confidence, do well across different areas in their lives. He continues.
People who regard themselves as highly efficacious act, think, and feel differently from those who perceive themselves as inefficacious.
They produce their own future rather than simply foretell it.
In other words, what he's talking about here is that these people are scribes in their own lives. They create their own lives as opposed to their lives being prescribed by others.
They're more resilient, better able to deal with hardships and difficulties. In other words, better capacity, as we discussed earlier, to deal with difficulties.
Now, the important thing about this research and his research over the years is that it can be learned.
It's cultivated over time.
So it would be useless if, in terms of research, at least for us, if he would say, well, some people are born with it and others are not.
Some people are born with what they started to talk about, the resilient gene,
and others are not born with that. But that's not the case. What he has shown is that it can be learned. It takes time, it takes effort, and we'll talk about later how we do it.
But the important thing, it's malleable. We can do something about it.
Other research by Curry on college athletes, I know there are many athletes in this room,
She showed that 56% of your success as an athlete, once you start being an athlete,
is determined by levels of hope, by how much you believe that you are going to succeed.
Remember from the very first or second class where I talked about the research by John Cotter, about the business HBS graduates,
were the two things predicted success in the long term, extraordinary success of these grads. One was that they were constantly asking questions,
and two was that they believed in themselves.
They thought they could do well.
But it's important to also realize that it's not 100% of the variance that's explained by hope or by belief or by optimism.
as many of the self-help books would have us believe.
But it's certainly part of the equation of success.
Nathaniel Brandon has been a therapist for 50 years, has done a lot of rigorous philosophical and psychological research and work on the concept of self-esteem.
We'll visit him more in depth when we talk about, when we have the week on self-esteem.
But for now, just a quick quote, the level of our self-esteem, in other words, the level of our belief in ourselves, has profound consequences for every aspect of our existence.
How we operate in the workplace, how we deal with people, how high we're likely to rise, how much we're likely to achieve, and in the personal realm with whom we're likely to fall in love,
how we interact with our spouse, children, and friends, what level of personal happiness we attain.
very low levels of correlation between material affluence and well-being
or between where we live and well-being
very high correlation between self-esteem and well-being in most research what we find is a 0.7 correlation between the two constructs
this is what I found in my dissertation as well so self-esteem matters the internal matters
And what we're doing when we enhance, when we raise our levels of belief in ourselves is we're transforming our mind.
We're changing the form so that we see the world differently. We perceive different things.
We experience things in a different way, whether it's successes that we then celebrate or failures that we then learn from and turn into opportunities.
But so much of it is about what we have inside here.
Brandon, self-concept is destiny
very similar to whatever your mind can conceive it can achieve from Napoleon Hill the only difference being that he also
puts a lot of rigorous thinking and research there and shows the limitation of the belief
here's another example of research done in this area which most people know about the placebo effect you go to the doctor, you have a headache the doctor tells you here I have a pill for you.
The best thing just came out recently. It will help you get over the headache. It gives you the pill, you get over the headache.
Unbeknownst to you, what she gave you was a sugar pill. But because you thought, because you believed that it will help your headache, it actually did help your headache. Real phenomenon in medicine.
So Herbert Benson from across the river, from the medical school here, has done a lot of research in this area.
Let me share with you just two of his studies.
What Benson did was bring in women who were pregnant and who had stomach problems, were vomiting, they were throwing up,
they were nauseous,
something which is relatively common, especially in the first trimester of pregnancy. So he brought them in and told them, I have this new pill for you that will help you
overcome your stomach distress, you won't throw up anymore after this. It's a very powerful and good pill.
So he gave them that pill, and they got over their stomach distress. They were better.
They didn't know, of course, that this was just a placebo drug, just a sugar pill.
Then he took it a step further, brought in another group of women with the exact same stomach distress with same vomiting, gave him a pill. He told them would help them overcome
their stomach distress. Only this time, instead of a sugar pill, he actually gave them small
dosage, not dangerous, but a small dosage of Ipecac. Now, those of you who know what Ipecac is, it's a drug that we take if we want to throw up. So if we have food poisoning,
We take this drug and it will actually elicit vomiting.
So he gave him this drug. And again, this passed all the ethical reviews and it was not dangerous.
That's what he did.
And these women were told that they'd get better.
And they did get better.
Not only did they not vomit as they should have done, more so with the Ipecac, they actually stopped.
Let me read to you an excerpt from his book, which I highly recommend.
Timeless healing.
I quote.
poisoning, these pregnant women with documented stomach distress thwarted the action of a drug
that should have made them even sicker. With beliefs alone, they cured themselves.
Now, this doesn't mean that drugs don't have an effect. You know, I don't recommend going home
now and, you know, giving your roommate, you know, Ipecac or even worse, cyanide and telling them And this is actually vitamin C. They will probably not feel better or healthier as a result.
But what this experiment does, and many others like it show, is the powerful effect of the mind, which we shouldn't discard. We need to study and understand.
Or here's another experiment that Benson writes about in his book. This was done in Japan.
So people who were allergic to a specific plant were brought into a lab,
had their eyes closed and then they had this plant touch their forearm and then they had another plant touch their other forearm and they didn't know which was which
and of course the plant that they were allergic to the arm flared up they were allergic to it after all
but then there was a second condition these people were told that the actual drug that they were allergic to
touched their left hand.
And another plant that they were not allergic to touched their right hand.
But Benson reversed the effect.
So actually the plant that they were allergic to touched their right hand. The plant they were not allergic to touched their left hand.
So they were supposed to flare up on their right, not on their left. But because they believed that their allergic plant
was on the left their left hand flared up the right hand did not based on the
power of the mind once again this does not mean that the external doesn't matter and that we attract everything that we want to into our lives but it does mean
that the mind plays a very important role in creating our physical certainly emotional cognitive as well as external reality beliefs very often become
self-fulfilling prophecies. But how does it work? How does it work? Let me share with you this
model that I created based on a lot of research in the field that essentially tries to explain
how our beliefs, our expectations impact our performance, whether it's through the placebo
drug, whether it's our performance in school, in sports, in relationships, in every area in our
lives. In other words, what comes in the box here, or in the oval here? What mediates
between beliefs, expectations, and actual performance in the real world? I want to talk
about two mechanisms. The first one is very straightforward, relatively simple. It's motivation.
So if I believe that I can do well, and think about your own past experiences, when
you believe that you could do well in something, you're much more likely to be motivated than if you think that you're hopeless and have no chance. You're much more likely to resign
and not do anything. You're much more likely to be motivated before the event, whatever the event may be, in training, in practice, as well as during the event, while it's taking
place. Think about what Marva Collins did. She motivated her students. She made them believe that they could achieve, that they could make something out of their lives, that
it was their responsibility, that it was up to them, and they've made all the difference for them because they were motivated. They worked hard.
So motivation makes a difference. There is another thing, though, in addition to motivation, and that is the notion of consistency
or congruence.
What does that mean? You see, we all have a mental schema of the world.
A mental schema of the way the world should be, ought to be, or is.
For example, I have a mental schema that suggests that things fall when left in mid-air. So I have a schema that says that if I drop this, it will actually fall.
I have a schema about my ability in mathematics, that I'm either a good mathematician, that I have potential in this area, or not.
I also have a schema about other people. I like this person. That person is a nice person.
Versus this person is just not nice, cruel.
So we have schemas about other people, about ourselves, about natural phenomena.
This is inside the schema. And then there is the outside world. In the outside world, actual things take place.
So, for example, when this is left in mid-air, it falls.
This has nothing to do with my schema.
It's outside. It happens regardless of my schema.
Now, I have certain potential in mathematics, regardless of my schema.
A certain person behaves generously and benevolently toward other people or in a hateful manner toward other people, regardless of my schema.
so there is what's inside
and what is outside
and here is the key point you see the mind does not like when there is a discrepancy between what is inside
and what is outside the mind likes when there is consistency
congruence between the two and if there is no congruence if there is no consistency consistency, then we experience a sense of dissonance.
Then we experience dis-ease.
It doesn't feel good. It doesn't feel right. And we do very often everything that we can to get the two on par again, either by changing
the external reality or by changing our mind to match the external reality.
We don't like when there is inconsistency.
There are a few ways in which we can create this consistency again. Let me share with you just some of them.
And I'm going to share four. They're interconnected. There is relationship between. There is overlaps. But just so it helps you think about it.
It helps you understand the dialogue that takes place between what is inside or what is inside and what is outside.
So the first thing we can do when there is a discrepancy, when there is inconsistency between the two, is update schema.
This is the first thing we can do. So I didn't know things fell when left in midair. Now I know I updated my schema.
Or I thought that person was actually hateful, but I just saw them behave so generously and benevolently.
Now I update my schema. It's a nice person.
The second thing that we do, which happens much more often than the first one, is ignore or discard external information.
We ignore or discard external information that doesn't match our schema.
We don't like this inconsistency.
We just throw the inconsistency out, so to speak, by ignoring it, discarding it.
The third thing we do, we actively seek confirmation.
We actively seek confirmatory data.
I mean, think about number two and three. Think about in the realm, you know, we're in the midst of election year.
Think about the person you're not going to vote for or the person you didn't vote for.
What we do, very often, let's say, I see President Bush doing something good, actually fighting for a cause that I believe in.
But I didn't vote Bush, for instance.
Very often what I would do is ignore and discard that information.
And then look for confirming evidence that will suggest or that will confirm to me why I don't like Bush in the first place.
The same regarding, you know, say the future elections, Hillary or Obama.
If I dislike them, I will look for confirming evidence why I dislike them.
And even if they do things that I like and value and believe in, I very often will ignore these things and discard them.
And what you're doing here, you're creating a reality. Because you're asking a question such as, where has Bush done terrible things?
Or where has Hillary or Obama did terrible things? And when we ask these questions, we completely ignore, discard, not see the positives.
Remember when I asked you about the geometric shapes? You didn't see the children on the bus, even though they were right there in front of your very eyes. So we know that questions create reality.
And in order to maintain this consistency, we do very often one of these two things.
Either ignore and discard or seek confirming evidence, positive or negative, to back up our schema.
Hillary Obama is good or Bush is good or whatever it is that we're thinking about.
The first thing is much more directly creating a new reality.
What kind of reality existed before the 6th of May, 1954?
It was a reality in which four minutes was the limit of human ability.
And what did Bannister do?
He said it's possible and then he changed the external reality. Not just for himself, but also for other runners in the world. And suddenly a new reality was created.
Initially the schema was four minutes is not possible. or rather four minutes is not possible and everyone adhered to this schema.
Roger Bannister came along and said it is possible
and changed that reality not just for himself but for other runners who were there.
The thing though is that after we perform with high motivation or low motivation,
mind looking for consistency, all that is left for us to do is interpret our performance.
Was it successful or not successful, good or bad? And there are two forms of interpretation.
One is the objective interpretation. Did I just get an A on the exam or did I get a C?
Did I just come third or did I come last in the race?
Did I just beat Princeton in hockey on Friday or did I lose to Princeton, go Harvard?
So what happened?
This is the reality. It's objective.
It's objective. But then there is also the subjective interpretation based on my beliefs. Let me share an example with you.
This is a story told about Thomas Edison.
Thomas Edison, back in the 1870s, was working, along with the rest of the scientific community, on the light bulb, on generating light from electricity.
The entire scientific community, or much of it, was working on that issue with no success.
Thomas Edison being no exception.
A journalist from one of the local papers came to Thomas Edison to interview him. He was already famous by then. He had invented many things. And they were talking about various things, and then they got to talk about the light bulb.
And the journalist said to Edison, Mr. Edison, you've been working on the light bulb for many years.
The rest of the scientific community has been working on it to no avail.
Now, at that point, Thomas Edison had conducted 5,000 experiments, and the journalist knew that. So he told Edison, Mr. Edison, you've conducted 5,000 experiments.
And you failed 5,000 times. Give it up.
Now, Thomas Edison, some of you may know, was also hard of hearing. In fact, one of his patents was a hearing aid.
So he said to the journalist, excuse me, what did you say?
The journalist said, well, I said you failed 5,000 times.
Give it up.
So Edison responded, I didn't fail 5,000 times.
I succeeded 5,000 times. I succeeded in showing what doesn't work.
Same objective reality.
Performance, 5,000 failed experiments, but very different interpretation.
The journalists and many other people in the scientific community conclude it's not possible.
The interpretation, subjective interpretation of Edison,
it's just another stepping stone towards success because it is possible.
In fact, Edison declared, before he had the light bulb, that on the 31st of December, 1879, he would display the light bulb.
That was long before he had done it. On the 31st of December, 1879, Edison displayed to the world, generating light from electricity.
Just like in 1962, John F. Kennedy said that there would be a man on the moon by the end of the decade.
And that was before we had the materials necessary for doing it, before we had the other technology necessary for doing it.
He threw his knapsack over the wall and said, it's possible to do it.
And that created a reality. That was coupled with a lot of hard work.
Edison, in fact, failed more than 5,000 more times before he actually created the light bulb. It wasn't just sitting in his room and saying, I believe, therefore I will achieve.
It was, I believe and I will work even harder now with more motivation and so on.
One of his mantras, I failed my way to success.
It is no coincidence that Edison, by far the most creative and productive scientific genius of all time,
he patented 1,097 patents in his career.
Much of our world looks the way it looks, thanks to him.
No coincidence that the most successful creative scientist in history
is also, as far as we know, the scientist who had failed the most times.
Research by Dean Simonton, we'll talk about it much more in depth when we talk about perfectionism. Research by Dean Simonton shows that the most successful scientists and artists throughout history
were also the ones who failed the most times.
No coincidence that Babe Ruth, who hit during many of the years when he played the most home runs, also hit the most strikeouts in five of these seasons, or struck out the most times, rather.
The most successful people in history are also very often the people who had failed the most times. This is a sentence that I'll repeat over and over again in the class, and here it is.
learn to fail or fail to learn learn to fail or fail to learn there is no other way to succeed
there's no other way to learn in terms of learning how to walk and there is no other way in terms of
learning how to succeed as a scientist or as a politician or as an artist the artists as dean
simonton showed who had the most duds the most failed attempts throughout history were also the
artists who are the most successful in the long run. No shortcuts. It's not enough to just sit
down and think and conceive and believe. We need to do much more than that. Marty Seligman,
considered the father of positive psychology, has done a lot of work on optimists and pessimists.
And here is what he found. What he found was that when it comes to goal setting, pessimists are realistic in terms of their short-term goals as well as in terms of their long-term goals.
That's a good thing to be realistic. Short-term goals as well as long-term goals, realistic.
Whereas optimists, on the other hand, are unrealistic when it comes to their short-term goals, but are realistic when it comes to their long-term goals.
Why is that?
Well, let's look at the model again.
So let's take the pessimists first.
they have a certain goal and they have low expectations low levels of beliefs they don't think they would do well low levels of motivation the mind looks for consistency and their performance is
usually according to their beliefs and expectations and their interpretation is I told you so
I told you I couldn't do well here and everyone else in a chorus says yes you told us so how wonderfully realistic of you
but then sometimes the pessimists succeeds beyond his or her expectations. And then what happens? Their interpretation is
low levels of beliefs. So the interpretation is, well, it was lucky. It was because Mars was in front of Venus.
And that only happens once every 50 years.
Won't happen again. Or it was my lucky day. Or
she just played very poorly today. And then the mind looking for consistency, they go around the loop again and again.
And then become realistic once more.
Unsuccessfully realistic, but realistic.
So they're realistic in the short term as well as in the long term.
Let's look at the optimist now.
The optimist starts with high levels of beliefs, high levels of expectations.
Motivation, incredibly high. The mind looking for consistency.
Performance, not so good. Not as good as the expectations were.
In other words, unrealistic.
However, the interpretation, because of high levels of beliefs, the subjective interpretation is, OK, so what have I learned from it? This is an opportunity. I've actually gotten better this time.
What have I learned? And they still have high levels of beliefs and high levels of expectations.
Motivation is high. The mind looks for consistency. They perform.
Still not good. Not as good as they expected. Unrealistic.
But their interpretation, still, what have I learned from it? I've gotten even better this time. I've shown what doesn't work.
And they continue. But then comes the chorus from the outside and says, come on, really? Why can't you be realistic like your good brother or sister, the pessimist?
But they believe that they can do it. And they continue to persist and to work hard again and again, five times, ten times, sometimes 5,000, even 10,000 times,
until they bring the quote-unquote unrealistic reality and make it realistic to match their beliefs over time.
So even though in the short term the reality may not match, I may run the mile for the next 10 years in 4 minutes and 12 seconds or 4 minutes and 2 seconds.
But I'll get there eventually and make my unrealistic, quote-unquote, expectations and goals realistic through a lot of failure, through a lot of hard work, through a lot of persistence.
What Seligman shows about optimism and pessimism is not that it's just some Pollyannish feel-good, you know, conceive-and-believe kind of approach.
Rather, it's about how we interpret events. So, for example, how do I interpret my failure as end of the story, catastrophe, give it up, or as an opportunity for success?
So he distinguishes, and we'll talk about it more next time, he distinguishes between interpreting an event as permanent or temporary.
I just didn't create light from electricity.
So that could mean, well, it's not possible and I'll never do it. Or it could mean, well, this is another step towards success, showing what doesn't work.
I've just been turned down from a job that I wanted.
Well, it means I'll never find a job. Or that's a temporary setback. Let's see what I can learn. Let's see how I can hone my search and find eventually my ideal position.
It's also about being pervasive or specific. Pessimists look at things as being, the negatives, being pervasive.
Well, I'm just not a good scientist.
Versus, well, I just wasn't able to get this experiment right this time.
Or if I get a poor grade on an exam, I'm just stupid, pervasive, everything, all or nothing.
Versus, I just didn't do well here on this specific exam. What can I learn from it? How can I do better next time?
This is what optimism and pessimism is. And it can be learned.
A lot of research in this area, a lot of research in this area showing how learning to interpret events subjectively as optimists leads to much higher success.
Some of you may recognize Matt Biondi, 1988 Seoul Olympics.
Many people thought that he could equal Mark Spitz's record of seven gold medals.
First race, silver medal.
Huge disappointment.
Second race, bronze medal.
Huge disappointment. Everyone, I remember that very distinctly. People talking about how he falls under pressure, how he's not the person we thought he is.
Marty Seligman at that point said, no, he's going to succeed. Why? Why? Because he measured him and many other athletes on their levels of optimism and pessimism.
And Matt Biondi was a consummate optimist. And he knew that he would interpret these quote-unquote failures. I mean, you know, bronze and silver medal in the Olympics, failures, right?
But these relative, for him, expected to win seven goals, failures, he would interpret them not as permanent, I choke, I can't make it in the Olympics,
as pervasive, I can't swim well anymore and win. Two, temporary and specific, which he did exactly that and won the next five gold medals.
Surprising many people, not Seligman and his research team, who knew exactly what his interpretation style would be following these quote-unquote failures.
Also associated with mental and physical health.
For example, our immune system, psychological and physical immune system, is actually stronger as a result of being optimists.
Resilience levels.
A lot of research by Karen Ravich shows that if you teach people to interpret things positively, optimistically, they're much more likely to succeed.
Those of you who are interested in more about this, her book, The Resilience Factor.
Karen Ravich, fantastic book, where she talks about programs implemented where within a few weeks, kids are immune to the experience of depression two years hence.
People who learn to be optimistic, and she teaches them in a short period of two weeks, compare that to the five years of the Cambridge Somerville study.
Within as little as two weeks, people who are taught optimistic interpretation style become happier.
Those who learn it are eight times less likely to experience depression.
Eight times less likely to experience depression if you simply learn a different interpretation style.
I haven't failed 5,000 times. I've succeeded in showing what doesn't work.
So what if I didn't do well now? I will do better next time or the time after that.
People who learn to interpret things more positively actually live longer. And we'll talk about some of this research. You read about a bit of it, the non-studies and so on.
People who interpret things positively, who are more optimistic, actually live longer. Now, that doesn't mean that all pessimists die young and all optimists die old.
That's just one of the factors that goes into the equation. There are many other things.
You know, you don't want, there's also unrealistic optimism that we'll talk about in a minute. You know, a person who's optimistic and says, I'll live till 120 no matter what, and smokes, you know, 120 cigarettes a day.
will probably not live to 120.
So it's not just about the belief, but a lot of it is.
And finally, as I mentioned time and again, it can be learned. And we'll talk about how it can be learned and how we can learn.
And you'll do it whether it's in your response paper, not for this week, but for the next week, as well as in sections, as well as by yourselves.
A technique that can be learned and can have all these positive effects.
Okay, there's a problem here, though.
You know, how do I distinguish between this and realistic optimism and unrealistic optimism, detached optimism,
that is advocated in, for example, the self-help movement? Is everything that I think of, I achieve and conceive and becomes a reality?
Is my self-concept my destiny and my only destiny?
Or is there such a thing as unrealistic beliefs?
And there is such a thing as unrealistic beliefs.
Here is an example.
Her name was Rina.
She was a showgirl.
At least to me she was.
Rina and I had a great deal in common. We were both in our teens.
I was 12, she was 14.
We both were in our fives. She was 5'6", I was 5'1".
I was in love with Rina. Rina, too, was in love with herself.
Now, just as a side note, I have a wonderful mother, an amazing mother, who believes in me.
And in fact, when the three of us, we were three brothers and sisters, would come home from school, we would very often talk to our mom about everything that was going on in school, good and bad.
So I came home after I realized that I was truly and madly in love with Rina and that she was the one for me.
I came home and talked to my mom about it.
And I told her, Mom, I love her so.
So she said, what's the problem? And I explained to her that she was older than I was, that all the big boys in the school were interested in her.
that she was much taller than I was.
And my mother believed in me and went on a self-fulfilling prophecy campaign.
And though she had never read Napoleon Hill, she said to me, Tal, whatever you conceive, whatever you believe, you can achieve.
And though she had never read Brandon,
she said to me, Tal, your self-concept is destiny and Rina is your destiny.
And she told me that if I truly, truly believed that I could,
that Rina would want me. She really would want me.
And my mom inspired me and made me believe in myself.
So I went ahead to approach Rina.
And I prepared for it.
I really prepared for it.
though i wasn't shaving at the time i put on aftershave and i continued i can do it i know i
can and i approached rina but then the music stopped though i had very high expectations
and though i envisioned success i closed my eyes and i saw myself succeeding she was not interested
She didn't want me.
However, however, we became very good friends.
In fact, so good that she would tell me about all her shallow and tall boyfriends.
Now, when my mom told me that, she really believed in it. She thought I was, you know, she told me this in Yiddish.
She said, you're a groysimitsia, which means in Yiddish, you're a big find.
I was really my, you know, really I was my Jewish mother's kosher pig malian.
So bad, yeah.
You know, that took me a lot of time to think about, so you better appreciate it.
Thank you, thank you.
But it didn't work.
And again, don't get me wrong, I'm very grateful to my mom. I literally had 24-7 Marva Collins in my house.
I owe so much to my mom. However, in this case, it probably was not the realistic belief.
So what is realistic? How do we identify what is realistic and what is not?
Here are some ideas to help us do so.
The Stockdale Paradox.
It's about finding the tension and reconciling the tension. And it's not easy. Again, I'm not going to give you a formula now to tell you,
okay, here is, calculate this, and if it's above a seven, go ahead with Rina. Below seven, probably not so.
There is no formula, but here is just a heuristic, something to think about when you think about beliefs.
Jim Stockdale was, Admiral Jim Stockdale, was the highest-ranking prisoner of war in the Vietnam War.
And he started to notice a phenomenon. He was there for years, eventually got out and lived to tell the tale. Many others did not.
And he saw many people survive, many people not survive, the very harsh conditions of the prison. And what he found was that the people who survived had two characteristics.
characteristics. First of all, they believed that they would get out. They had faith that one day they would be free. They would get to see their family, their friends, and this faith kept them
going. At the same time, and this is the second component, they had realistic beliefs and evaluation
of the situation. If any one of these two components were missing, they were unlikely to survive. If they didn't have faith and they didn't believe that they would survive, they were
very likely to die in the harsh conditions. On the other hand, if they thought that they would
get out by this coming Christmas and really believe that they would get out by this coming Christmas, they were also less likely to survive because they didn't get out by this coming
Christmas and then they were despondent, resigned, helpless, and very often they died. So it was the two components believe that you would get out but at the same time know that you need to deal with
reality and that it's tough here is what jim stockdale said you must never confuse faith that
you will prevail in the end which you can never afford to lose with a discipline to confront the
most brutal facts of your current reality whatever they might be realistic optimism now
the thing is that you may be wrong at times and sometimes you may really believe in something
and believe that you have realistic expectations and not succeed. But as we talked about and as we'll talk about
in a few minutes, it doesn't matter that much. Because even if we don't succeed, we just bounce back up and continue working hard. The key though is as much as
possible to attain this balance, what Maslow calls the graceful integration
between high levels of beliefs and connection to reality.
No prescription here, but just a heuristic, something to keep in mind.
Positive thinking is not the secret.
Yes, it's absolutely part of the secret.
Yes, it's part of the success formula. It's part of the happiness formula.
But it's not all.
False optimism, sooner or later, means disillusionment, anger, and hopelessness.
Here is the secret of success. This is a secret proven by research.
Thousands of years of research on successful people in different cultures, in different places, in different ages.
It's optimism, passion, and hard work.
It will be very hard for you to find successful men and women throughout history who did not have all three.
Optimism, belief, faith that they can do well, that they can succeed, passion, love for whatever they were doing, and hard work.
There is no substitute for hard work, as Edison said.
These three components, the secret, simple, straightforward, you know it all. Remember what I said during the second class. I'm not going to teach you much new. I hope to remind you of what you already know.
Optimism, passion, and hard work.
Does luck play a role?
Absolutely.
Jefferson, I'm a great believer in luck, and I find that the harder I work, the luckier I get.
There is actually a science behind luck, and you'll read about it in The Luck Factor,
where people who have these three components, who believe that they can do well, who love what they do and work hard, actually find more luck,
in the words of Thoreau, in common hours.
Okay, so why don't all parents teach us to have high expectations? If it's so good for us, if it's related to success, to happiness, to physical well-being,
Why don't all parents, why didn't all our parents just say to us, wherever we were, you can succeed, you can do it. If you dream about it, you can do it.
Why did very often did parents and people who care about us lower our expectations?
Because they were concerned about our happiness.
They were concerned about our self-esteem.
You see, there's a lot of belief, people believe that high expectations naturally lead to disappointment.
So, high expectations lead to disappointment. And it sounds right.
I mean, this is a formula that was written in the 19th century by William James.
He said that self-esteem is equal to our success over pretensions.
In other words, our achievement, how much we succeed, how much we achieve, over what we pretend or what we aspire to, what our goals are.
In other words, if we have high expectations, high pretensions, we're much more likely to hurt our self-esteem.
For example, let's say my aspiration, my pretension, my expectation is to make $4,000 a month.
Again, I'm just throwing a numerical example here because it's easier to understand. Let's say my hope is to make $4,000 a month. That's my pretension.
But in fact, what I end up making is $2,000 a month.
According to William James' formula, my self-esteem, and as we know, self-esteem and happiness are very highly correlated and related.
My self-esteem, my happiness level, according to this formula, is a half.
On the other hand, let's say my pretensions, my expectation is to make $1,500 a month.
And, in fact, I make $1,500 a month.
According to this formula, my self-esteem, my happiness level is 1.
So here, even though I'm making less, and again, I'm using a numerical example here. You can think about other examples.
Even though I'm actually making less here, my self-esteem and my happiness are higher.
So lower your expectations.
Not so.
What was found in the last 35 years of research is that this formula is actually wrong.
That's not the case.
Here is how it actually works.
Let's say we have a graph.
And this is time.
And here is my self-esteem levels and happiness levels.
And let's say I start off around my base level, which is here.
And then I have a midterm in positive psych.
And I don't do as well as I expected to do. What happens to my self-esteem? What happens to my happiness?
Of course, it will go down.
It's natural. We all want to succeed, or most people want to succeed. So it goes down if it's below my expectations. But very quickly, as the research by Daniel Gilbert shows on effective forecasting,
very quickly we go back up to our base level of happiness.
And then a week later I have another midterm in, say, math 55.
And I ace it.
I get much higher grade than I expected.
and what happens to my self-esteem and happiness goes up
but then very quickly goes back down again
and then let's say I'm 12 years old
and I walk down the street and I meet Rina
and I ask her out
and she says no
what happens to my self-esteem and happiness It goes down slightly.
And then, very quickly, it goes back up again.
And then, lucky me, I walk down the street, and I think I see Rina, but there's something different about her. And it turns out she has a twin sister.
And I ask her out. And she says, no.
and what happens once again slightly down but then I recover and go back up again
and you won't believe it
they're identical triplets
and I meet the third sister
and she says yes she says I love you too and what happens to my self esteem and happiness it goes up slightly right even taller than this
but then very quickly back down to base level and so on and so on
the vicissitudes of life whether I get tenured or not get tenured whether I win the lottery or lose money the ups and downs
around a base level of well-being
now there's good news here and there is bad news here
the good news, I can take more risks it's not the end of the world if she says no
it's not the end of the world if I fail here or if I don't get my dream job
it's okay, I'll recover, we all do so that's the good news
the bad news is, so I'm stuck
so I was born with this base level according to my genes and I can't really improve how do I raise this base level of happiness
and it's possible
And we'll talk about, the whole course is about raising this base level of happiness.
But here is one finding from specifically the research on self-esteem. On one thing that you can do right now when you get out of class to raise self-esteem.
And that is to cope as opposed to avoid.
To cope, meaning to put yourself on the line.
To take risks, not when you're in your panic zone, but when you're in your stretch zone. To risk failure.
to handle things, to deal with things, to confront things
that are important to you, to try out for that play, to speak out in section if you haven't, to go out to a place where you really want to go but are a bit shy,
to try, because people who cope
over time have the same or sometimes more ups and downs, but their ups and downs look
like this. Still ups and downs, permission to be human, but the base level increases.
Why does the base level increase? And I'm going to end here. Why does the base level increase when we cope rather than avoid? For three reasons. First, self-perception theory.
Daryl Bem, I think either Dartmouth or Cornell. What Daryl Bem showed was that we derive
conclusions about ourselves in the same way that we derive conclusions about others.
So, for example, if I see a person going up to people and, you know, initiating a conversation or speaking up in section or trying out for plays and trying again and again, my conclusion
about this person, oh, this person is courageous.
This person must have high self-esteem.
And I may derive the conclusion about myself in exactly the same way.
By seeing myself behave in a certain way, I reach a conclusion about my self-esteem or benevolence or generosity or whatever it is.
Self-perception theory. And if I cope, if I try things out,
then I see, oh, this is a person with courage. This is a person who tries.
And my conclusion about myself will be, oh, I must have high self-esteem. And my self-esteem, as well as happiness levels over time, will actually increase.
Self-perception theory, we derive conclusions about ourselves in the same way that we derive conclusions about others, meaning by looking at behavior.
When we fail after coping, we realize that the actual pain that comes with failure is far less than the pain that we imagine and that we associated with failure.
Oh, I just got over it. Okay, so I didn't do well here. Or she said no. But I got over it. Whereas when I imagine it in my mind, I think it will last forever.
Just like those tenured or non-tenured professors thought that their pain would last forever. Whereas it goes away.
So when I realize that the pain of actual failure is far less than the pain associated with failure, I become more confident. Hey, I can handle it.
I'm actually much more resilient than I thought I was.
And my self-esteem increases. My happiness as a result increases too.
And finally, there is more success because there is no other way to succeed. There is no other way in terms of learning how to walk.
There is no other way in terms of succeeding in art or in science or in business or in politics.
Learn to fail or fail to learn. I'll see you on Thursday.